[Music]
welcome to future focus a video series
brought to you by ICICI Lombard today we
have with us gopal bhatta children the
CFO and CEO of ICICI Lombard as you all
know ICICI Lombard is a leading non-life
insurance company today we are here to
talk about risk management in these
unprecedented times Gopal is going to
share with us insights from ICICI
Lombard and also insights for you as an
audience
welcome to the show sir how are you I'm
good Michele thank you so much and good
morning everyone
it's always great feeling to be here and
happy to kind of share elements of risk
management that we fundamentally have
implemented our business is
fundamentally risk management I think
let me put it in that context and and as
we shall rightly describe will be
extremely happy to kind of share our
thoughts we are also gaining experiences
as we speak but extremely happy and
delighted to kind of speak on the areas
which we think will be relevant and
useful to all of you so before we get on
to the subject you joined ICICI Lombard
in 2002 when it was a very young company
you just finished your CA and your
company secretary and you'd come in at a
time when a crisis are just ended like
the.com crisis and here we are in the
midst of another crisis risk management
is back to the center of everything you
know how did you how do you manage to
understand these changing trends you
know I wanted to talk to you about a
couple of things based on your
experience before we go on to the main
question no absolutely I think that's a
good question to start off with Vishal I
think if you have which is what I said I
think if you look at it from a nice ASIS
numbered standpoint fundamentally we
take the risk of companies and we kind
of get the companies away from their
risks that they are exposed to and we
kind of ended in dignified in case if
any losses are being experienced by them
as a result of some of these crisis
events we make good those loss
I mean that's all the journey starts for
us so in that sense as an organization
as a company we are into risk management
all the times and as it is rightly said
the thing starts from within I mean you
have to kind of while you are advocating
a lot of risk management practices for
companies but more importantly you need
to see as to how you have instituted a
risk management capability within the
organization which will fundamentally
stand the test for meeting any risks
that the company would be exposed in the
first place and our journey to risk
management in fact to be honest started
almost like about 15 years back we
didn't start off with an enterprise disc
management frameworks in the time when
we started operations because we also
wanted to gain ground in terms of our
experiences and we kind of thought about
it somewhere around 2006 2007 to kind of
start looking at putting in some kind of
a framework within which we will be able
to work as an organization and we have
been kind of learning ground over the
years and Hana Street was in 2009 2010
is when we really thought about putting
a formal erm framework which will kind
of fit the organization at large that's
how the old journey started and from
there all and as I said every experience
is a learning experiences more
importantly when you come across
crisises they kind of teach a lot
because it's a testimony of what kind of
practices you have put into and even
this crisis as we speak obviously of an
unprecedented scale again it teaches a
lot in terms of how companies have to
function when you look at it from an
earing perspective
great points are you also wrote a
current blog a recent blog which talked
about risk management you know in that
you outline a few important points are
the roles and responsibilities can you
share some roles and responsibilities of
yourself that you are handling this
situation in such an unprecedented time
piece absolutely Vishal again that's a
great question to ask so again as I said
I think being a responsible company I
think we are driven by our core
fundamentals of corporate governance and
risk manager
and as I said in these times we continue
to remain committed fully so far as
meeting the service requirement of our
customers are concerned now when you
look at it from the standpoint of a
responsibility or a challenge in these
times one of the core things that stands
the test is what is it that you stand
for as an organization
I mean that's the pillar in which the
foundation of the organization is laid
out and if you look at one of the things
that Isis Lombard has advocated at all
times is profitable growth I think
that's the theme that we have kind of
driven the organization with and that
along with ensuring protection to our
balance sheet at all times has been at
the core of the forefront within which
we drive all our responsibilities and
the challenges that we have in so far is
meeting the requirements of the
customers are concerned the couple of
responsibility that comes immediate when
you look at this scenario one is around
the I mean I'll kind of talk about three
aspects the first and the foremost
aspect is employee safety because that's
the first responsibility that comes when
you look at any organization that is in
the service industry employees comes
first
and so therefore you have to ensure the
safety and the well-being of the people
so that's one of the four core
fundamentals that I would kind of lay
emphasis on when it comes to
responsibility in such situations the
second is business continuity because
end of the day as we say employees can
come employees may leave but the
organization has to kind of survive for
the next X number of years so hence to
that extent while events of a pandemic
nature or otherwise may happen
institutions have to kind of completely
reorient their business models and look
at ways of sustaining operations insofar
as instituting appropriate business
continuity practices so that's the
second area where I would kind of lay an
important responsibility on and the
third aspect which is more with respect
to our own internal disc assessment
because when I said as an organization
you have built an ERM framework in place
you need to make sure that you do a
comprehensive risk assessment of your
internal processes and see where do you
stand
in these uncertain times now let me
quickly touch upon some of the
initiatives or let's say aspects that we
have taken in to ask into factor when we
look at it from an employee safety
standpoint the first and the foremost I
mean pretty much so I'm sure you have
heard a lot we also kind of did in all
our office promises temperature checking
for our people and if at all any of our
employees showed any symptoms of this
particular virus being contracted
because you need to kind of make sure
that those set of people for whatever
reasons need to be treated differently
so that the rest of the organization is
able to function as business as usual
the second thing that we did was
obviously in these times a lot of us I
mean particularly we are in the business
of service we tend to do a lot of
physical trainings and conferences for
most of our employees as well as for our
service providers so in these times we
again said let's keep that on hold and
we can always as we are doing this
digitally I think the thought process is
try and see if you can kind of do a lot
of those in the digital format the third
aspect I think what we did was
completely put in that sense full stop
to all kind of travels whether it is
domestic or international because again
we didn't want the employees well-being
to be compromised and the final piece
it's always important not just to have a
committee at the top I mean while you
can have a tone from the top in managing
things but the eyes and the ears of the
organization is always have to be on the
ground so we kind of adopted a
two-layered
approach when it comes to when it came
to sports so while at the at the
management end we had the man calm but
at the operating level we had those
point of contacts who also acted as the
eyes and ears for the organization so
those were some of the measures that we
took insofar as employee safety is
concerned quickly on the internal risk
assessment which was the second pillar
that I kind of spoke about as an
organization we have and erm framework
in place the erm framework brought
kind of works around five key risk
categories one is credit risk market
underwriting operational and strategic
now each of this risk areas kind of has
an impact or has a responsibility in the
way of how you manage it
let me just quickly take you through
each of them if you take credit risk we
are exposed to credit risks on working
with our reinsurance partners just like
we take a risk from customers we also do
a risk transfer to reinsurance partners
we have to ensure that we do a
comprehensive risk assessment of those
reinsurance partners so that any
possibility of recoverability from those
three insurers are being looked at very
closely so that's a creatress monitoring
that we do on the market risk side I
mean if you look at an insurance
company's operations we do write or
let's say we underwrite risk of
customers but we also manage the funds
of people because we invest that in
various securities and in the process we
are exposed to market risk so again
there becomes a responsibility for us to
very closely monitor the assets in which
you have kind of invested so that you
don't run any kind of risk in terms of
recoverability of those investments and
at the same time there is equally a
responsibility to ensure that you have
adequate liquidity because only when you
have liquidity in the portfolio is when
you are able to manage most of the
things
so hence market risks milk market
becomes equally an important priority on
the underwriting risk that forms the
core of our business and in these times
there is a responsibility for us to
still continue exhibiting underwriting
service the question is how do you get
that done so there again I think
thankfully the level of investments that
we have done on the digital capability
we have been able to do a lot of virtual
risk inspections even in these times we
have been able to carry out a lot of
let's say virtual claim service and in
the process you are able to as I said
run the business as business as usual
scenario
so again underwriting risk assessment
becomes of paramount importance
operating operational risk is equally
important in this
times because couple of reasons one you
know system risk becomes off at
heightened levels because all of us are
now getting used to let's say a work
from home environment and this by itself
poses a lot of challenges and you need
to make sure that your system related
information security aspects are
completely assist and all kind of
endpoint security is what you are
required to Institute they are all up
and running so that employees are able
to still function as effectively as they
could and in the process still there is
no compromise of customer data or for
the matter of fact even there is no
leakage of data that the organization
gets exposed to so ends operational risk
is of paramount importance so there
comes a responsibility to manage that
aspect and finally on the strategic risk
side reputation risk is of great
significance because an organization
fundamentally stands for the brand that
it is associated with and unless and
until you don't manage the brand
effectively you can significantly be put
to test so there again I think we tend
to look at I mean these days there are
lot of avenues available by which you
can do those social media tracking we
also pretty much end up doing a lot of
those so that at the end of the day we
just want to make sure that from a
reputation standpoint we don't lose our
brands credibility so those are all
aspects that I would say insofar as the
responsibilities in these times are
concerned and you asked one more
important element Vishal which was on
insofar as challenges are concerned now
if you look at challenges let me look at
the various stakeholders that we render
service to its customers first right so
in these times on the one side while
there's a challenge in the way you
operate but equally there is a need for
you to exhibit service to the customers
so that's by itself is an inherent
challenge and you need to kind of
capacities the institution by which you
are able to meet the requirement of the
customers so that's one of the
challenges that you're kind of exposed
to it as an insurance company we tend to
work with distributors because when you
call up distant
it's agents it's my bank partners it's
let's say my dealer partners so there
are various distributors that you kind
of work with and again in these times
it's important for us to handle them to
make sure that they are able to adopt
digital technology because as I said you
need to continue business to the extent
it can be as usual and to end to the
addiction there is a challenge for us to
ensure that there is acceptance of the
wave we have created the organization we
also want the intermediation to be
capacitated as well so you may have a
challenge to meeting the requirement of
the distributor
there is a regulatory angle because in
these times the regulator comes out with
a lot of let's say regulatory guidelines
keeping in mind the policyholder
interest so and there is a lot of
compliance requirements that they have
eased but at the same time you have to
make sure that as an organization you
stand to the requirement of the
regulatory norms that are being laid
down so again there's a challenge to
meet the various regulatory guidelines
that will get laid out and the final
piece is there is equally a challenge
that you have with respect to overshadow
dozens bill because equally shareholders
while they understand the situation but
at the same time they would logically
expect reasonable growth in profits
insofar as the organization is concerned
so that in a nutshell is what I would
say are the various nuances of
responsibilities and the challenges that
we are exposed to as a company very good
answer said I mean in a sense I want to
straight away move into balance sheet
protection because all those
responsibilities that you mentioned
protect your balance sheet and focus on
you know how to fight the volatility
right there is increased volatility
going forward so would you recommend
that protecting the balance sheet is a
single most important factor at this
point of time and focus on growth at all
costs and where you see growth coming
from I think in these times even
customers tend to value a lot of
companies which are on a very strong
solid footing and that would be evident
by the balance sheet strengths that you
have at the same time they would value
you for the extent of
capital adequacy or solvency that you
are able to exhibit relative to the
minimum norms that are prescribed by the
regulator and at the same time they
would equally look for the level of
corporate governance that you are able
to exhibit as an organization and since
you specifically touched upon the aspect
of balance sheet protection as I said
one of the core risks that we write as a
company is mind writing risk and in when
I'm underwriting risk particularly let's
say for large factories there is a need
for us to undertake physical disk
inspection because only when you are
able to understand the risk of
effectively is how you are able to price
for the assets that you are insuring now
in these times it's very difficult for
us to carry out any form of a physical
risk inspection but at the same time the
fact that you are ensuring the risk
requires you to come out with a solution
which still meets the requirement of
underwriting and at the same time you
don't put your balance sheet to risk so
what we have done again over the years
the journey that we have traversed in
respect of our investments in technology
we have been able to undertake virtual
risk inspections and these mechanisms
have been created by which we are able
to carry out this virtual inspections
prior to underwriting the risks and in
the process there is a live video
streaming that happens of this
inspection survey that we do and thereby
we are able to kind of underwrite the
risk at the same time and ensuring that
our balance sheet is not exposed to
undue risks that could come and hit us
in the future
so that's one example of how we are kind
of managing the balance sheet risk when
it comes to the core aspect of
underwriting even on the claims side I
mean one of the key requirements while
the extent of claims could be slightly
lower in these times but equally for the
claims that come through it's important
for us to ensure that claims service
continues now there again I think some
of the investments that we have done is
on the motor side we can do a live video
streaming of the motor assessment of
claims on the property side I mean there
are very recent examples where there was
a factory which
what impacted on account of damages in
these times so we were able to deploy
drones and survey the location and in
the process we are able to kind of
assess the extent of damage with
otherwise we would not have been able to
do unless and until we would have
invested in those capabilities so again
we are ensuring that the customer aspect
is taken care of and equally the risk
that is associated to the company is
appropriately managed through technology
based interventions so there again it's
a case of how we are able to protect our
balance sheet and so far as your other
thing which you asked on growth I think
in these times we have actually seen
couple of growth opportunities getting
played out now let me give an example of
two three areas how we see growth
playing out for us on the corporate side
one of the things that Isis Illume bird
has done over the years is built direct
relationship with corporates and that
stands as a testimony in these times
when the corporates generally as I said
would want to place an insurance with
the company which is time and tested and
they just want to kind of make sure at
this times not to look about for an
alternate insurance partner so and April
1 as we all know is a big day for
corporate renewals because most of the
corporates mirror their renewals to the
financial year cycle and thank happy to
report that most of the corporates that
were due for renewals on April 1 we have
been able to kind of get those renewals
and that has seen reasonable level of
growth momentum sustaining the small and
the mid corporates within that has been
an area of focus for the last 3-4 years
in particular for us and there I think
we have significantly advocated use of
digital capability through robotic
assistance driven mechanism we call it
as Myra my robotic assistance and in
these times and particularly for the
month of April and May we run a campaign
on the SME side and happy to report that
almost 90% of the policies that we have
sold on the SME side has been able to be
done through digital adoption and the
growth
mentum is quite positive so SME is
looking very good for us quickly talking
about the retail side if you look at on
motor we all know that there is no
growth happening on new vehicle sales I
mean because most of the Williams and
dealerships are pretty much not
functioning completely while in the last
week or so we have seen some kind of
relaxation happening but at least till
now most of them were closed so the only
Avenue through which most of these
points of distribution are able to make
margins let's say the dealers is to be
able to continue retaining the existing
customers of theirs and a lot of
emphasis of us has been to kind of
promote retentions or print continued
renewals of the existing customers and
there we did make an acquisition in
quarter three of the last financial year
which called from unbox technologies and
today in these times that particular
acquisition has come in very handy
because we have been able to deploy the
crm platform at the points of
distribution and we have been able to
significantly make the benefit of being
able to retain a larger number of
customers so again we see growth
momentum sustaining on the motor side as
well and finally on the health side this
is an event like any other catastrophic
event it is an event of a pandemic
nature which impacts the health of all
of us and as I'm sure if you would have
asked this question three years back let
me ask to you Vishal who do you have
taken a health insurance cover maybe
three or five years back no actually not
I would have not taken a comprehensive
comprehensive cover or even for the
matter of fact he would have polled the
people of thousand people three years
back and asked them to raise hands on
how many of them would have had a health
insurance covered why I would not be
surprised if very few number of hands
would have kind of gone up now that's a
state of situation where we are in so
far as health penetration is concerned
and events of a pandemic nature clearly
impacts the health of all of us and it
that by itself presents an opportunity
and today the point that you made while
you would have taken some form of health
insurance
covered but the extent of coverage would
not be adequate you look at yourself
what kind of course we incur while going
to an Hospital while you may not want to
have that situation coming through but
indeed if it does happen the extent of
money that we have to shell out is
significant
so again health clearly presents an area
of opportunity for growth and there is a
clear silver lining that exists insofar
as that particular segment is concerned
so in a nutshell that is what I would
say in terms of how we are protecting
our balance sheet and at the same time
looking at different segments in terms
of growth leavers as well okay it's a
great point again I have two questions
combined now I think it's easy because
we've covered a lot of it there are
emerging risks because of the co 819
situation and there is an existing risk
yes okay and you've often said that risk
management should be you know not a
compliance function but a business
function yes right how do you assess the
situation at this point of time
organizations have to handle emerging
risks you know current risks and make
sure that it's not a compliance function
who do you go and tell in the
organization that please look at it as a
partner function and let's manage this
risk together so I think let's look at
it this way right I think as I said it's
all about let's say the culture of the
organization I think the it's if you
have a culture which kind of ensures
that every employee of the organization
is sensitive about the function that he
or she is handling then they by itself
understand what risks that they are
exposed to so to that extent I would say
the foremost point which I would make is
with respect to what kind of a culture
does the organization imbibe and if you
have a will lead down culture across the
organization then to that extent
managing risks in even in these
adversities or even in these uncertain
times seems to be relatively much more
easier now let me look at couple of
risks that could be risks in the past
and certain risks which we could kind of
face as we
get through this event let me talk the
ones which is the latter part I mean
some of the new new-age risks that we
are exposed to in these times which
becomes of much more significance now
the point that I made was as I said I am
sure every organization is looking at
one in these times to have most of that
people working from home which is but
natural to have that situation in place
and that by itself opens up a set of
risks that we are exposed to on the
cybersecurity front and we know the
importance of cybersecurity there have
been instances of wanna cry petia and
similar kind of I mean we can keep
taking names and these are events which
have in that sense put organizations to
test and therefore in these critical
times while there is a need from a
business standpoint to have your people
operating from your homes
but equally at the backend there is a
need for you to have your information
security team up and running and again
in a sector in which VR regulator
mandates us two things one they ensures
that you have an appropriate information
security policy to be put in place which
acts as a governance governing mechanism
which is approved by the board but more
importantly there is a designated chief
information security officer who has to
be an employee of the company and who
will be responsible for instituting
various security control measures so
that the organization is in that sense
protected from various vulnerabilities
that we are exposed to so to that extent
you also have a chief information
security officer and thirdly from a
governance standpoint what we have also
done between the board and the CISO we
have created an information security
committee which comprises of members of
the management committee who tends to
have an oversight on the various aspects
of information security so the first
aspect is culture the second aspect is
governance so that you have an
appropriate governance structure through
which you are able to manage this now
coming to specifics in terms of what you
can do in order to address
cybersecurity related risks in this
environment I think what we have done is
one we have taken a lot of initiatives
in kind of sending a lot of mailers so
far as the companies are concerned
because these days you tend to get a lot
of links you get a lot of emails saying
that if you click this you will get
whatever the benefits are so in that
sense we have done a lot of educational
mailers educational videos that have
been kind of put in place so that you
are able to manage the security risks
that you're exposed to that's one the
second thing when you are equipping your
employees to work from home there is a
need for you to protect the customer
data as well as prevent any form of
unauthorized use of the data that
resides with the people and what we have
instituted again is insofar as various
endpoint Security's are concerned now
endpoint Security's could be use of
various USBs and similar kind of access
drives is something that we have
prevented for the organization at large
so while you can continue working in the
hardware assets which are already kind
of screened and appropriately monitored
but at least insofar as any kind of data
leakage or data theft is concerned I
think there is a lot of endpoint
security that has been instituted
insofar as data protection is concerned
the second aspect which we have done
also to ensure that we have the
information security protected is a lot
of fishing activities is what we carry
out I mean we kind of send mailers
saying that you will get five days off
if you click this link that's a classic
way to test out if people get fished or
not now in the process a lot of us may
click and if you further click on the
further links then automatically there
is a pop-up that comes and says that you
have been fished so and that by itself
is an awareness that gets created in the
minds of people and and again there are
grids in terms of action
that are being taken in case if one
persists continuously on various fish
fishing attacks that we carry out so in
the process again you are able to kind
of manage the risk associated with cyber
security and I also understand we spoke
so much about risk risk appetite and
risk tolerance know who should set the
standards is is there a case for setting
standards to measure an organization's
appetite in tolerance when you look at
well-established standards whether it is
the ISO standard or whether it is let's
say the cosa standards that describe
requirements on companies all of them
lay emphasis on one of the most
important aspects which is thrown from
the top because that sets the context or
the tone for the risk appetite that is
being set for the organization so that's
very very important and from our
standpoint again the risk appetite is
something that gets set at the board
level because the board determines basis
the businesses that we are into we kind
of set what kind of appetite that we
want to set for ourselves as an
organization and then comes in terms of
governance we do have the Risk Committee
of the board which oversees our
adherence to the risk update that has
been said and then you have let's say
the management who kind of takes it
forward insofar as compliance to the
risk appetite statement that is laid out
but the most important thing is setting
a tone in so from the top and there
again if you look at from a nice little
home but perspectives one of the things
again we are possibly the first Indian
company at that point of time be back in
April 2008 18 when there was this ISO
31000 2018 standard that came into place
it certifies institutions all risk
management practices and what they look
for is three aspects one is the risk of
earnings that domination has said second
is a risk culture that again the
institution has adopted in their erm
practices and the third is the internal
processes that the organization has
instituted in so far as the control and
self assessment framework is concerned
so when we got this ISO 13
thousand standard compliance done
through british standard institution we
were the first Indian company at that
point of time to be certified under the
ISO 31000 2018 standard now that by
itself in that sense give us some
credence insofar as governance culture
and our processes are concerned and when
it comes to appetite of my thought
processes you should set your appetite
only with two or three key matrices you
can't have an appetite statement which
runs into let's say a full page in terms
of number of appetites that you want to
set for yourself is a novelization but
more importantly when you set those two
or three appetite as a part of risk
appetite statement it's important to
kind of merge it with the national
objective that you have I mean as a
company you can have a visual on what is
it that you want to be known for your
appetite should revolve around it that's
the foremost requirement in second
aspect when you look at an appetite it
is it can be either a quantitative
statement or it can be qualitative
statement there's nothing wrong in
either which face when you look at
defining an appetite for the
organization but my personal preference
is to have a qualitative assessment or a
qualitative risk appetite laid down or
quantitative risk appetite laid down so
that the ease of measurement against the
appetite becomes relatively better when
it comes to tolerances unlike where I
said it will be tone from the top
insofar as tolerances are concerned
because these are aspects that impacts
individual risk elements of the
organization it has to be bottoms up
because these are people who are
actually running the operations running
the shop and in the process we are kind
of actually experiencing the risk that
they are exposed to the does technology
play a major role in tracking appetite
and tolerance absolutely I think when
you look at the appetite is more like I
would say a high level appetite
statement that gets defined but
definitely when it comes to tolerances
there is a need for you to have a
technology
which can aid you to kind of one look at
what has been the actual outcomes
visibly the tolerances that have been
set and in the process give you a
mechanism by which you are able to know
the various triggers that can get
alerted and you can speak into action
a classic example some of the risks that
I kind of outlined is let's say let me
take a simple example of a market risk a
market is today is the most important
risk element when you look at it from
the current event standpoint and you
need to have a trigger which tells you
like because of the market Falls of
whatever percentage what has been the
impact on your portfolio now that impact
unit portfolio impacts your solvency or
impact your capital adequacy how do you
have enough capital to be able to meet
the fall in top prices one such examples
of how you can kind of monitor your
tolerances similarly when it comes to
operational risk I think one of the
risks that maybe I didn't did not speak
at length is fraud I mean in these
uncertain times there is a lot of
tendency for people to do frauds I mean
if you go back to 2008 times or whenever
you see have seen any crisis is playing
out because people are stressed
companies are stressed for their profits
individuals are stressed because of
their income levels are relatively lower
there is a tendency on people to commit
some form of a fraud or the other so
hence you need to make sure that your
fault fraud tolerances should kind of
trigger immediate alerts so that you can
immediately swing into action and you
were able to course-correct
the need of the earth the economy
firstly do you see a silver lining okay
and how many bounced back you know there
have been questions from the audience
saying limping back or normalcy or
bouncing back right I would rather have
bouncing back because you're all working
and we all want to have good lives what
are your thoughts on economy let's talk
about the macros at this point of time
all this country come back along with it
all those companies and offer those
great jobs from a macro standpoint if
you look at non life insurance
sector that was opened up to private
participation in 2001 if you look at
over the last 20 years the sector has
grown at a compounded rate of 17% which
is almost 2 enough times the growth in
GDP of the country and you given growing
at 17% levels hardly you will see
industry is growing at 17% kegger over a
20-year period but despite that if you
look at one of the measures of
monitoring is insurance penetration as a
percentage of GDP if you look at the
Indian market it's a point nine seven
percent if you look at global average
it's two point eight percent if you look
at the BRIC countries they all raise I
mean particularly when you look at
Brazil when you look at China when you
look at South Africa they are all having
penetrations which are in excess of
between 1.5 percent to 2 percent levels
India stands at 0.97% so that by itself
is a huge potential insofar as the macro
numbers are concerned now when you come
to specifics let's talk three key
product lines where one sees a silver
lining
let's take motored if you see motor is
by far the largest product line for the
market 40 percent of the industry plus
is motor insurance of the 24 crores
vehicles that are plying on the road
more than 50 percent of the vehicles not
have an incidence that's the reality of
the situation right the while they're
having some regulatory changes that have
happened in the last 1 and 1/2 years but
more than 50% of the vehicles today are
these without an insurance now currently
again as I said we can speak about new
vehicle sales not being there we have to
focus on renewals but the long-term
prospect of the ability to convert some
of this non penetrator or under
penetrated segments into the ambit of
insurance is a huge opportunity let me
ask you we shall any guesses on what
proportion of what proportion of the
population has got a health insurance
cover say 2 percent so let's say 2
percent so that could be more on the
individual side now when you look at
health insurance it's a cover that an
individual takes for self or family
vehicle that an employer takes as a
coverage for their employees
or it could be a government that can
sponsor a MassHealth program for the
vulnerable section of the society today
if you look at what you said is
absolutely right in an individual
context that penetration is actually 3%
but when you see your bank on you're
almost there
but when you look at the larger picture
in terms of all of these three segments
put together that number roughly stands
at about one third only one-third of the
country is in some form of an insurance
or the other so there is a huge Headroom
available in terms of the opportunity on
the health insurance pace and by the way
when you talk about health insurance
today you are only talking of
hospitalization insurance our
out-of-pocket spends which is what we
end up spending for visiting a doctor
visiting a Diagnostic Center ordering
medicines through a pharmacy chain
availing of an ambulance service asking
for a second opinion
now all of these services is today not
covered through insurance at all and it
roughly constitute two thirds of our
health care spends and that's not
covered through insurance today at all
that's an opportunity and that's where
again I see somebody significantly
looking at tapping into the OPD segment
so that's an opportunity there take the
corporate space particularly SME and
when I say these are small corporates
which also have to ensure their assets
and ensure their people very few number
of corporates insure their people and a
limited extent of coverage is more even
they take insurance for their assets as
better so on the SME side again there is
a significant prospect insofar as growth
is concerned so in these times of in
that sense a possible gloom and doom for
the in the short term I think from our
standpoint from a nice is a number
standpoint we are very very optimistic
while there can be some temporary pain
as we speak let's say for fi 2021 but
insofar as the long-term potential of
the segment and the sector is concerned
it's quite enormous and there is also a
study that has been done by some of the
global reinsurers says if the country is
at a per capita level of 1500 to 2000
dollars which is where we are at this
point
time the growth of the insurance sector
will continue to be 2 to 2 and 1/2 times
the GDP of the country you would be
saying that it is going to be bouncing
back and not limping man my take on this
will be as I said fill the time we are
subject to this levels of lockdown there
will always be an apprehension on people
to get back to roads get back to buying
an asset so you will see some kind of a
temporary challenges insofar as growth
is concerned but then what is more
important is again the organizational
capability to be having a multi-product
multi-channel most multi customer that
will help them to at least kind over
this difficult times and so once things
comes back to reasonable normalcy there
is no reason why you should not see
growth momentum kind of coming back now
the question is whether it will come
back in h2 of the current here whether
it takes maybe more than a year to come
come back I think we will have to wait
for the jury to be played out but at
least from our standpoint we are
extremely excited and positive insofar
as the growth momentum we are getting
back to normalcy
okay great answer on a personal note how
are you spending time spending time with
family how are you spending time for
yourself
what are you doing so that's always a
difficult one right in these times when
you are radio at home never exposed to
this kind of a situation you always want
to kind of go out maybe reach out to
people talk to them is something that
you would always want that happening but
I think what they try to do is I think
largely unfamilar said and therefore to
that extent I like to spend time of
course with my all my members of the
family but more importantly my son he's
11 years so he's trying to learn a lot
of things trying to explore experiment
with a lot of stuff being at home I have
hardly been able to get so much time to
spend time with otherwise normally I
would say him only in the night and
maybe early in the morning that's those
so in that extend yes I spend a lot of
time with my family and the second thing
is I think I try to also do my daily
routine exercises I spend at least about
30 minutes because it's extremely
important to keep your body and mind
flexible again in these times so you
have to be so that you mind tends to
work sharply through those routine
exercises every day and thirdly try to
do a little bit on the sporting side as
well while at this times 1 is not equal
to do that but they generally like
playing badminton and more importantly I
like listening to music so that's how I
kind of stay engaged Gopal you've been a
wonderful guest and I'd love to host you
again thanks for being on future purpose
thank you ICICI Lombard thank you for
everyone including you in these times
please do stay safe stay healthy that's
very very important for all of us to
come out of the situation thank you
thank you everybody we look forward to
having you on another episode of future
focus very soon bye Gopal the next
thanks we shall
[Music]